<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
<title>Tatsumoto Ren</title>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/index.html</link>
<description>How to use Free Software to learn Japanese, and more.</description>
<language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 21:17:49 +0300</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 21:17:49 +0300</pubDate>
<atom:link href="https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>If you're almost done with Tango N5, is it worth switching to the KanjiTransition deck?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>No.
The <a href="learning-kanji.html#jp1k-method">JP1K method</a>
was invented so that people can skip RTK
(or any other <a href="learning-kanji.html#isolated-kanji-study">isolated kanji</a> study deck).
For a lot of people learning kanji out of context is boring and difficult.
The benefit of the JP1K method is that you can start learning
from authentic Japanese sentences almost from the start
instead of spending time on memorizing individual characters.
If you've basically finished the <a href="basic-vocabulary.html#anki-deck">Tango N5</a> deck,
it's safe to assume that you've already got enough kanji reading ability
to continue learning vocabulary from native content.
Moreover, the <a href="jp1k-anki-deck.html">KanjiTransition deck</a> is largely based on Tango N5.
The only thing that's different is the card template.
So there's no point in studying the same material twice.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-worth-switching-from-tango-to-jp1k.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-worth-switching-from-tango-to-jp1k.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2023 23:37:21 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Why shouldn't I just keep using an app instead?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>We do not recommend &quot;language learning&quot; apps like Duolingo, Lingodeer, Babbel,
and others due to the fact that their methodology conflicts with <a href="whats-ajatt.html">AJATT</a>'s
principles of <a href="whats-immersion.html">immersion</a> learning.
Such apps do not actually help you with anything.
There are no success stories.
On the other hand, AJATTers typically reach fluency in just 18 months.
The apps prevent you from reading interesting content in your target language, such as manga.
And they make you more miserable in the end.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/why-shouldnt-i-just-keep-using-an-app-instead.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/why-shouldnt-i-just-keep-using-an-app-instead.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 20:17:30 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Does playing Japanese audio on repeat while I sleep count as immersion?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>It doesn't.
And, generally, it is not recommended.
But if you understand the mechanics behind this idea,
you may consider doing it and get some, although little, benefit.</p>
<p>It is important to note that humans cannot learn anything while sleeping.
There is no research that suggests that we can.
As far as I know, the idea was popularized by the old AJATT website.
AJATT is about <a href="mass-immersion.html">mass immersion</a>, doing Japanese all the time.
The reason why some AJATTers have Japanese audio playing
when they sleep is not because you can learn something while you sleep,
but because you will be hearing Japanese speech
just before falling asleep and just after waking up.
You can be exposed to the language more by doing this trick.
If you pause Japanese before going to bed,
there will be some time,
maybe just a few minutes,
when you are not immersing.</p>
<p>The other side is that
any additional learning progress that could be made by the extra listening time
will be canceled out by low-quality sleep.
Playing audio while you're trying to sleep can disrupt you.
If you're constantly being jolted awake by the audio,
you're not going to get the restorative sleep you need to function at your best.
Sleeping properly is an essential aspect of the language acquisition process
and should not be compromised.
A solution would be to use some technology to pause the audio after falling asleep
and resuming it just before it's time to wake up.
For example,
an alarm clock app that has a feature to trigger a podcast app or a music app
instead of playing a preset alarm sound by itself.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/does-playing-japanese-audio-on-repeat-while-i-sleep-count-as-immersion.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/does-playing-japanese-audio-on-repeat-while-i-sleep-count-as-immersion.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2023 10:54:22 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How strict do you recommend being about 1T?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>In
<a href="is-it-ok-to-make-cards-for-sentences-i-dont-fully-understand.html">Is it OK to make cards for sentences I don't fully understand</a>
I said that ideally you need to be strict
about making only <a href="one-target-sentences.html">1T</a>  sentences.
I think being strict definitely helps
because it removes unnecessary ambiguity from the SRS reps.
If there's no other way,
making MT cards occasionally won't do too much harm though.</p>
<p>Try to avoid MT cards where there are two or more words you don't know.
They may slow you down, and they may be too difficult to review.
Trying to learn two things on one card uses a lot of mental energy,
and it can be boring and frustrating.
Learning 1T sentences is more fun, they are quicker to grasp.
If everything is easy, you'll enjoy studying more.</p>
<p>You can make MT cards once in a while,
but it's smoother when you don't.
Once you get more advanced,
you will not need to make MT cards because there will be
already enough 1T cards you can find just by continuing to immerse.</p>
<p>If you are in a situation where you want to create a TSC to learn a word,
but the sentence contains two or more unknown words,
first create and learn a 1T card where the other unknown word is the target.
By doing so, the original sentence will transform into being 1T.
Then you can learn the original sentence as a normal 1T card.</p>
<p>In summary, it is best to primarily create 1T flashcards
and only occasionally make MT cards.
By following this strategy, you will optimize your time
and energy while making consistent progress towards fluency.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-strict-do-you-recommend-being-about-1t.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-strict-do-you-recommend-being-about-1t.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 15:25:33 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How do I change an environment variable?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>In the <a href="table-of-contents.html">guide</a>
I sometimes instruct to set or change environment variables.
Environment variables provide a way to store simple settings
that can be accessed and used by various programs and scripts running on the system.
Changing environment variables is a common task for users,
and it can be done in different ways.
I'm going to present you the easiest way, and you can read about other ways on Arch Wiki.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-do-i-change-an-environment-variable.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-do-i-change-an-environment-variable.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 00:09:11 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I have a deck I haven't reviewed for a whole year. Should I reset it?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>It can be tempting to reset a deck that hasn't been reviewed in a while,
but I do not recommend doing so for the cards have a review history.
Despite feeling like you may have forgotten everything,
you likely remember more than you realize.
Instead, I suggest reviewing the overdue cards.</p>
<p>If you select the deck and review the overdue cards,
the cards you still remember will increase their intervals significantly,
while the forgotten cards will not lose their intervals completely,
as long as you have <a href="setting-up-anki.html#new-interval">new interval</a> set to a value greater than <code>0</code>.
In the end, this approach will require you to review fewer cards than if you started from scratch.</p>
<p>By contrast,
If you reset the deck,
you'll have to relearn each card again,
with each card graduating with an interval of <code>1</code> day (or the value you set in settings).
You'll lose any progress you have made on cards that you still remember.</p>
<p>If you find yourself struggling with a backlog of cards,
consider reading <a href="how-to-review.html#fighting-backlogs">Fighting backlogs</a>.
The most important tip is to store overdue cards in a filtered deck
and take small chunks for review.
With this approach,
you avoid overwhelming yourself with hundreds or thousands of cards at once.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/should-i-reset-a-deck-i-havent-reviewed.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/should-i-reset-a-deck-i-havent-reviewed.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 17:21:10 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How do you recommend starting on listening practice?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>There's really not that much to it.</p>
<p>The way I learned to understand spoken Japanese is by watching raw anime.
If you're a fan of anime, you'll find this method enjoyable and engaging.
Anime is easy to understand
because it is voiced by professional voice actors who typically speak clearly
and use the standard Japanese dialect.
This ensures that you're learning from high-quality,
accurate sources of spoken Japanese.
Moreover,
anime covers a wide range of vocabulary,
including both formal and informal expressions.</p>
<p>But how do you make the most out of this practice? Here are some tips:</p>
<ol>
<li>Watch an episode first without subtitles or translations.
This helps you focus on the sounds of the language rather than relying on written cues.</li>
<li>After watching, read the Japanese subtitles and learn any unknown words.
This expands your vocabulary
and helps you notice the words when you hear them again later.</li>
<li>Extract the audio track and listen to it multiple times using <a href="passive-listening.html#mpd">mpd</a>.
You will hear and notice the words you've learned recently.
Repetition helps train your ear to distinguish individual sounds and patterns.</li>
</ol>
<p>Mastering a language takes time and effort.
But as you continue to practice,
your listening abilities will improve and you'll be able to easily
comprehend more and more of what you hear.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-do-you-recommend-starting-on-listening-practice.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-do-you-recommend-starting-on-listening-practice.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 16:54:05 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I immerse with English and Japanese subs on at the same time. Is this a bad idea?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>If you watch with English and Japanese subtitles on the screen at the same time,
consider having both subtitle tracks hidden most of the time.
In <code>mpv</code> you can press <kbd>v</kbd> to toggle subtitle visibility.
When you feel like you didn't understand something,
turn the subs on temporarily.
Mpvacious has <a href="https://github.com/Ajatt-Tools/mpvacious#secondary-subtitles">key bindings</a>
that let you toggle secondary subtitles as well,
or you can have them appear on mouse hover.</p>
<p>You can approach this question at 2 levels.</p>
<ol>
<li><p><strong>Training your listening ability.</strong></p>
<p>Displaying both Japanese and English subtitles simultaneously
would occupy a significant portion of the screen,
making the subtitles difficult to ignore.
If you have them visible all the time,
it is likely that you will end up reading them.
It may happen unconsciously, automatically, accidentally.
Even if you catch an outline of a sentence in the corner of your eye,
it could give you a hint and disrupt your listening practice.
If you're genuinely committed to improving your listening skills,
consider <strong>hiding all subtitles</strong>.
This is the only way to ensure that you're not cheating.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Increasing your overall comprehension.</strong>
To ensure effective learning,
it's crucial that you don't read English subtitles.
If you do,
and if you don't pay attention to the Japanese subtitles,
<a href="should-i-watch-anime-with-english-subtitles.html">your progress will be zero</a>.
Try to understand the Japanese subs first.</p>
<p>If you must use English subtitles,
try to make them less accessible,
such as requiring a button press or mouse movement to reveal them.</p>
<p>Then consider whether English subtitles can help you,
or if it is better to get rid of them completely.
Prioritize understanding the Japanese subtitles first,
and only opt for English subtitles if necessary.
As I previously discussed in
<a href="should-i-put-english-translations-on-bilingual-tscs.html">Should I put English translations on Bilingual TSCs</a>,
relying on translations doesn't help in language acquisition.
While they may help you understand a rough meaning of a sentence,
they don't aid in understanding how ideas are expressed in Japanese,
and how grammar works.</p>
<p>Furthermore,
using English subtitles carries the risk of creating false associations
between English words and Japanese words with similar meanings.
This can lead to biases in your Japanese comprehension.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>In conclusion,
it is OK to keep Japanese subtitles visible,
but English subtitles are better kept hidden.
Hiding both English and Japanese subtitles is good for improving your listening abilities.
And if you hate going forth between turning subs on and off,
consider <a href="is-it-harmful-to-always-have-tl-subtitles-on.html">watching some shows fully raw and other shows with Japanese subs always on</a>.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/en-and-ja-subs-at-the-same-time.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/en-and-ja-subs-at-the-same-time.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 04:28:06 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>What's the best way to make use of an iTalki teacher?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>I'm beginning to utilize iTalki.
many iTalki teachers seem open to structuring a game plan based on what each student requests.
What would you consider to be the most effective use of iTalki
in a way that's complementary to the AJATT philosophy?
What would you personally look for in a teacher?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't know much about iTalki, so I went to their website
and was surprised to see that it doesn't work with JavaScript disabled.
Truly a disappointment.
I couldn't press half of the buttons on the webpage,
all I could do is read the text on the few pages that were able to load.</p>
<p>So apparently Italki is a platform where you pay to have lessons with language teachers.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>英語 のスキルが確実に向上する方法をお探しですか？
italki には資格を持つ 英語 講師が在籍しています。
英語 のオンライン講師のレッスンを受けて、英語 力アップを目指しましょう。</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the world of language learning,
paying for speaking practice is often compared to paying for sex.
So you're about to do something really shameful there.
I do not think that iTalki can be utilized in a way that aligns with the AJATT philosophy.
AJATT has always been about learning by yourself,
and on this website I also stress it a lot.
Ask yourself,
would another native speaker of your native language
pay you to have a conversation with you?
Would you pay a native speaker of your native language to have a conversation with you?
Probably not, right?
The reason some people are paid to speak is that what they say is of value.
Famous businessmen, scientists, programmers, politicians are paid to
give talks and lectures
because they share valuable knowledge,
not because they speak a certain language.
The value of a conversation lies in its content, not simply in the act of speaking a language.
Having a meaningless conversation in another language
with a language teacher is the antithesis of value.
A teacher's role is to teach learners how to learn by themselves,
and thanks to this site you already know how to learn your target language through self-study,
so you don't need to pay anybody.</p>
<p>If you are &quot;looking for a way to improve&quot; your target language,
you need to understand that
language is a tool for acquiring knowledge.
Speaking is merely a byproduct and a result of acquiring knowledge, not the end goal.
Output ability emerges as a result of listening, watching and reading for thousands of hours.
It is through input that learners acquire the necessary linguistic structures,
vocabulary, grammar,
and cultural context to communicate effectively in the target language.
Therefore, it is crucial to prioritize comprehension over production, input over output.
The best way to improve is by <a href="whats-immersion.html">immersing</a> in the authentic content
made for native speakers of the TL.
Immersion plus <a href="spaced-repetition.html">SRS</a> leads to comprehension ability.
Immersion plus comprehension leads to speaking ability.
Then, speaking ability plus speaking practice leads to speaking mastery.</p>
<p>Before you concern yourself with improving your speaking skills,
you need to make sure that you have mastered understanding your TL.
To be able to speak a foreign language well, you need to be able to hear well.
Pronunciation comes from listening.
If you can't hear it, you can't say it.
If you are able to understand everything you hear, you will be able to speak well.
In addition, a good grasp of the language's phonetics and pitch accent is vital.
Lastly,
research the topic you want to discuss and learn how native speakers converse about it.
You can't talk about something if you don't know how and what to say.
For example, you learn about history of Japan, and then you can talk about it.
Or you learn about Japanese food, and then you can talk about it.
To learn how to talk about something
you need to read and listen to native speakers of your target language.</p>
<p>Speaking practice can be counterproductive.
It is not uncommon for learners to <a href="early-output-or-reading-ahead-of-listening.html">start speaking early</a>
before fully developing their listening abilities
and intuitive understanding of language structures.
This can lead to the reinforcement of incorrect pronunciation and grammar,
and can actually hinder language learning progress.</p>
<p>Let's say you have immersed for <a href="mass-immersion.html">10,000 hours</a>,
and now you are ready to start improving your speaking.
Getting better at speaking requires speaking practice.
Speaking practice is mainly a tool for improving pronunciation.
First,
determine if dedicating time to this activity aligns with your objectives.
After 10,000 hours of immersion,
most individuals can speak proficiently
and can improve naturally by simply talking with native speakers on the topics of interest.
If the answer is yes,
AJATT recommends practicing by imitating native speakers.
This is done through shadowing exercises.</p>
<p>Shadowing is a language learning technique where you listen to a native speaker
and repeat what they say, trying to match their speed, rhythm, and intonation
as closely as possible.
Here's how you can go about shadowing:</p>
<ol>
<li>Choose an audio or video recording of a native speaker speaking your target language.
It could be a <a href="immersion-with-youtube.html">YouTube</a> video or an audiobook.
Obtain the text version, the transcript of the recording as well.</li>
<li>Listen to the recording.
Start shadowing by repeating what the speaker says,
trying to match their speed, rhythm, intonation and pitch accent as closely as possible.</li>
<li>Record yourself.
Pay attention to your own pronunciation and try to correct any mistakes you notice.</li>
</ol>
<p>You can repeat what the native speaker says after they say it or simultaneously, at the same time.
There appears to be no consensus on which way is better.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/whats-the-best-way-to-make-use-of-an-italki-teacher.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/whats-the-best-way-to-make-use-of-an-italki-teacher.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 02:33:03 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How much of my immersion should I understand?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>The answer is simple: you should aim to understand 100% of your immersion.
Everything.
One hundred percent.
Every time you come across an unfamiliar word or phrase,
it is a problem, and it has to be fixed.
Don't hesitate to take action, you've got thousands of words to acquire.
The ultimate goal is to reach a point where each unknown word is so rare
that it stands out, and you just can't ignore it.</p>
<p>When starting to learn a new language,
it's normal to understand nothing at first.
The first step is to train your ears to hear the sounds of the language, which can take time.
The next step is to immerse for thousands of hours and learn lots of grammar and vocabulary,
required to reach fluency.
The more time you invest, the more your language skills will improve.</p>
<p>To tackle the initial challenge of not understanding,
it's advisable to prioritize <a href="basic-vocabulary.html">basic vocabulary</a> in the beginning.
By spending your first month or two on learning the most common words of the language
you can quickly improve your comprehension and
start to understand everyday conversations quite well.
You can then continue learning by mining example sentences from your input,
starting with slice of life shows
and eventually moving towards more sophisticated media.</p>
<p><em>Frontloading</em> the most frequently used words is perhaps one of the most significant techniques
in mastering the target language,
which I personally found very helpful in the beginning.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-much-of-my-immersion-should-i-understand.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-much-of-my-immersion-should-i-understand.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 18:37:32 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
