<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel><title>Tatsumoto Ren</title><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/index.html</link>
<description>How to use Free Software to learn Japanese, and more.</description><language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 04:37:28 +0300</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 04:37:28 +0300</pubDate>
<atom:link href="https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item><title>
Ankidrone Sentence Pack</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Ankidrone Sentence Pack is an Anki deck
that contains over 44,000 Japanese sentence with native audio.
This deck is not to be learned from back to back,
its purpose is to aid you in finding example sentences
for your targeted sentence cards.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/ankidrone-sentence-pack.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/ankidrone-sentence-pack.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 04:28:05 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
How to review</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Though Anki is an excellent piece of software,
you can learn languages more effectively if you tweak some settings and know how to review.
Even if you're using Anki for something other than studying human languages,
this article may still help you.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-to-review.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-to-review.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 05:16:10 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Japanese fonts</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>On a freshly installed GNU/Linux distro
Japanese characters may not look pretty.
This can be fixed by installing
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Localization/Japanese#Fonts">Japanese fonts</a>
and creating a proper
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Font_configuration">Fontconfig</a>
configuration file.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/japanese-fonts.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/japanese-fonts.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 22:20:40 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
FAQ</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>This is Tatsumoto's AJATT FAQ.
You can search questions you're interested in if you press <code>Ctrl+f</code>.
I'm going to update this article as I receive more questions.
If your question hasn't been answered, ask it in <a href="join-our-community.html">our chat</a>.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/faq.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/faq.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jun 2021 02:24:53 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Mining from movies and TV-shows</title><description><![CDATA[
<p><em>Sentence mining</em> is the process of picking sentences from your immersion and making Anki cards.
Each sentence has one unknown piece of information,
which is referred to as <em>target word</em>.</p>
<p>To mine sentences from movies and TV-shows
you are going to need the mpv video player,
and a plugin for mpv called mpvacious.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/mining-from-movies-and-tv-shows.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/mining-from-movies-and-tv-shows.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 19:06:56 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Learning Kanji</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Unlike kana which you can learn in a matter of few days no matter what method you pick,
learning kanji is apparently more difficult, and there are many methods of doing it.</p>
<p>To pick the right method
you have to understand why you want to learn kanji in the first place.
The &quot;practice how you play&quot; principle applies here as well.
Kanji do not exist in a vacuum, instead they're used to writing Japanese words,
so in order to &quot;learn&quot; them all you need to do is learn words.
To learn a word means to memorize how it's read and what it means.
Over time as you keep learning words you unconsciously get better at recognizing the kanji.</p>
<p>We advise against learning kanji readings in isolation.
Very often a kanji character has a number of completely different readings.
Not only learning all of them is an enormous task,
but it's impossible to apply the knowledge to real native content when reading.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/learning-kanji.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/learning-kanji.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 06:53:51 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Resources</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>This is the Ajatt-Tools Resources List.
With the help of our community we've gathered the links to help you in your Japanese studies.
We prioritize libre software and content that you can download for free.
Everyone is welcome to suggest more resources in our chat.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/resources.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/resources.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 21:26:34 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Foreword</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Congratulations! You've taken your first step towards learning Japanese!</p>
<p>I'm Tatsumoto. I'm primarily known for a <a href="https://t.me/ajatt_tools">Telegram channel</a>
with focus on helping foreigners learn Japanese language.</p>
<p>This site is a quickstart guide for the subscribers
and anyone who wants to build a solid understanding of the Japanese language.
We focus on understanding before speaking, or input before output.
We believe doing so is the shortest path to fluency,
because you avoid whole groups of problems that come with premature output,
such as foreign accent and grammar mistakes.
This approach makes the journey easy and fun
because from day one you are encouraged to learn from compelling content
made for native speakers of your target language.
Most people who persevered and reached fluency
watched their favorite TV shows in Japanese
and read lots of books and manga every day.
No amount of brute force can get you there,
so forget about traditional approaches such as taking classes or hiring a tutor.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/foreword.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/foreword.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2021 02:38:26 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Setting up Yomichan</title><description><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://foosoft.net/projects/yomichan/">Yomichan</a> is a browser extension
with a pop up dictionary
that allows you to look up unknown words with the hover of a mouse.
On top of that Yomichan can be set up to create Anki cards from the words which you look up.</p>
<p>The process of picking sentences from your immersion
and making Anki cards is called <em>sentence-mining</em> or <em>sentence-picking</em>.
Each mined sentence has to contain one unknown piece of information,
which is referred to as <em>target word</em>.</p>
<p>You don't necessarily have to pick an entire sentence,
but if you're a TSC user it is not necessary to keep mined items short.
When you're out in the wild picking sentences, select the ones that are interesting to you.
Your goal is not to mine every word.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/setting-up-yomichan.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/setting-up-yomichan.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2021 02:24:07 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Donating to Tatsumoto</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Because almost all my content and the tools I make are offered free of charge
the Ajatt-Tools project relies on donations to stay alive.
We do not have ads or privacy-violating trackers, we are entirely dependent on you.</p>
<p>If this site or our free software projects were useful to you,
I'll appreciate if you donate to the Ajatt-Tools maintenance fund
to help me support myself and continue working on Ajatt-Tools.</p>
<h2 id="patreon">Patreon</h2>
<p>You can support me over at Patreon by clicking the button below.</p>
<p align="center">
    <a target="_blank" href="https://www.patreon.com/bePatron?u=43555128">
        <img alt="patreon" src="img/become_a_patron_button.png">
    </a>
</p>
<h2 id="monero">Monero</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.getmonero.org/">Monero</a>
is a privacy-focused and censorship-resistant cryptocurrency.
The transactions are all hidden.
There are many ways you can buy or sell Monero, one of the simplest ones is through
<a href="https://changenow.io/">ChangeNow.io</a>.</p>
<pre><code>47sD7pSagHF7mp41SwrDj4KF8dSj4kdK6YUZ9fkmnR8h587wVc1kW66iJy9m83maVjWXtDJxmCVxdieMyGZNFHZ2Fifrbr5
</code></pre>
<p align="center"><img alt="XMR QR" src="img/xmr_qr.png"></p>
<p align="center"><i>XMR QR</i></p>
<p>Thank you very much for your support!</p>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/donating-to-tatsumoto.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/donating-to-tatsumoto.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 20:58:53 +0300</pubDate></item>
</channel></rss>
