<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
<title>Tatsumoto's guide to learning Japanese</title>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/index.html</link>
<description>How to use Free Software to learn Japanese, and more.</description>
<language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 23:36:09 +0300</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 23:36:09 +0300</pubDate>
<atom:link href="https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>What is the difference between the Foundation and Essential decks besides the way the cards are reviewed?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p><a href="ankidrone-essentials.html">Ankidrone Essentials</a>
consists solely of cards from the JLPT Tango textbooks,
maintaining the original order and content.
The deck is designed for those who have completed Ankidrone Foundation
or wish to expand their vocabulary
and supplement <a href="sentence-mining.html">sentence mining</a>.</p>
<p>In contrast,
<a href="jp1k-anki-deck.html">Ankidrone Foundation</a>
takes the N5 subdeck from Ankidrone Essentials,
but the card order is rearranged.
We tried to arrange the cards so that each new card is <a href="one-target-sentences.html">1T</a>.
The sorting algorithm we used prefers cards
with the fewest estimated number of unknown words per example sentence
and puts them in the beginning of the deck.
The deck is intended for complete beginners who only know hiragana and katakana.
The <a href="learning-kanji.html#jp1k-method">JP1K method</a>
helps new learners get used to reading words with kanji characters
which can initially seem difficult.</p>
<p>Additionally,
many katakana words and place names have been removed from Ankidrone Foundation,
as they are typically unnecessary for learners.
For instance,
words like <code>コンサート</code> are straightforward since they are borrowed from English.
On the other hand,
Ankidrone Essentials includes these terms because they appear in the Tango textbooks.</p>
<p>We also introduced new cards into Ankidrone Foundation
when we saw that certain words needed to be learned before others to preserve the 1T order.</p>
<p>If you decide to skip Ankidrone Foundation
and jump straight into Ankidrone Essentials,
you will need to learn kanji and their readings from the beginning,
which can be more challenging compared to following the JP1K method.
However, this is a choice some learners prefer.
You will also need to suspend or delete any cards you already know,
as Ankidrone Essentials retains all content from the Tango textbooks.
And since Ankidrone Essentials does not maintain the 1T order
as effectively as Ankidrone Foundation,
you may encounter more unfamiliar words within sentences.
However,
it's worth noting that the Foundation deck is not flawless in this regard either.</p>
<p>If you have completed Ankidrone Foundation,
skip the Tango N5 subdeck in Ankidrone Essentials,
as they cover similar vocabulary,
differing mainly in card templates and order.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/difference-between-foundation-and-essential-decks.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/difference-between-foundation-and-essential-decks.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 23:30:51 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Ankidrone Anki Decks</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Our <a href="tag_decks.html">Anki decks</a> are organized into a comprehensive system
designed to guide learners through the process of mastering the Japanese language
using the <a href="whats-ajatt.html">AJATT</a> method.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/ankidrone-decks.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/ankidrone-decks.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 02:24:58 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Ankidrone Foundation</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>The most important part of learning Japanese with the
<a href="whats-ajatt.html">AJATT</a>
method
is to enjoy native content
and be able to grow your understanding of the language entirely through immersion
by picking up new words from the media you read, watch or listen to.
To transition towards learning directly from Japanese media,
first you need to level up your comprehension.</p>
<p><em>Ankidrone Foundation</em>
is an Anki Deck for newcomers to Japanese based on the JP1K method.
If you want to learn the theory behind this deck, please read
<a href="learning-kanji.html">this article</a>.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/jp1k-anki-deck.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/jp1k-anki-deck.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2024 05:43:12 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Ankidrone Essentials</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p><em>Ankidrone Essentials</em> is the generally recommended Anki deck for newcomers to Japanese
who want to quickly learn <a href="basic-vocabulary.html">basic vocabulary</a>.
Ankidrone Essentials is made to skyrocket your comprehension of native Japanese.
Since the first release in February 2020,
it has helped many people and received positive feedback.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/ankidrone-essentials.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/ankidrone-essentials.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 18:08:31 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mitigating the Impact of Early Output</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>I'm forced to output early. How can I mitigate the damage?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you're already living in Japan,
or taking Japanese classes,
you may find yourself in situations where you need to speak Japanese.
If you're not fluent yet,
<a href="introduction-to-learning-japanese.html#outputting">early output</a> will damage your Japanese.
In this article, we'll explore strategies to help you mitigate the damage.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/mitigating-the-impact-of-early-output.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/mitigating-the-impact-of-early-output.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 09:34:57 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Learning Kanji Radicals</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>In my previous article on <a href="learning-kanji.html">Learning Kanji</a>,
I mentioned that beginners do not need to
<a href="learning-kanji.html#learning-radicals">learn kanji radicals</a>.
However,
radicals play a significant role in the Japanese language.
Understanding the proper Japanese names for common radicals
aids in grasping spoken conversations about kanji.</p>
<p>The advice provided in this article is tailored for people
who already understand Japanese.
If you are still a beginner,
I recommend focusing on <a href="table-of-contents.html">more essential aspects</a> of Japanese learning.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/learning-kanji-radicals.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/learning-kanji-radicals.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 01:54:15 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How to type X with Fcitx?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>This article addresses common questions about typing with Fcitx.</p>
<p>To enter anything when using Fcitx,
type what you want to type and then press the space bar.
Fcitx will provide predictions for the characters you intend to insert.
If the prediction is incorrect,
continue pressing the space bar until you find the correct one.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Main article: <a href="how-to-type-in-japanese.html">How to type in Japanese</a></p>
</blockquote>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-to-type-x-with-fcitx.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-to-type-x-with-fcitx.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 01:44:07 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Is it best to make the monolingual transition as soon as possible?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>No.</p>
<p>There's a <a href="going-monolingual.html#when-to-go-monolingual">sweet spot</a>
for making the monolingual transition,
and doing it either too early or too late can reduce your efficiency.
In theory,
you could attempt to go monolingual very early in your learning journey.
You might learn just the most common 50 <a href="basic-vocabulary.html">words</a>,
the bare minimum of <a href="learning-grammar.html">grammar</a>,
and dive into using only the target language for definitions.
It would be very challenging, but it's not impossible.
I've seen people who went monolingual much sooner than I advise.
It was tough for them.
Although they struggled and were often lost,
barely understanding anything for a long time,
they eventually found their way.</p>
<p>So yes,
an early transition is possible.
However,
going monolingual too soon is not the most effective approach.
The difficulty is so high
that you might end up spending an excessive amount of time
doing <a href="going-monolingual.html#looking-up-unknown-words">recursive lookups</a>
and deciphering complex explanations in the monolingual dictionary,
which is not the best use of your time.</p>
<p>If the process is too difficult,
you'll likely spend more time lost in the dictionary than actually learning.
A more balanced approach is to expand your vocabulary
with the help of bilingual dictionaries first.
Then,
transition to monolingual dictionaries when you're more prepared.
This strategy allows for a smoother shift and sets you up for success.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-best-to-make-the-monolingual-transition-as-soon-as-possible.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-best-to-make-the-monolingual-transition-as-soon-as-possible.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 22:15:29 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Going monolingual</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>So far,
you have been relying on bilingual dictionaries to learn new words.
For those studying Japanese,
JMdict is a frequently used resource,
offering Japanese-to-English translations.
Going monolingual means moving from bilingual to monolingual dictionaries.
It is an important step forward in your language acquisition journey.
This shift is crucial for achieving long-term success and mastering the language.</p>
<p>In this article,
we will explore how to transition from bilingual to monolingual dictionaries effectively.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/going-monolingual.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/going-monolingual.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 11:08:05 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Avoiding bad advice</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Countless language-learning methods exist,
and each of them tells you to do different things.
Some methods are effective, but many are not.
Unfortunately,
the Internet is brimming with advice that might sound good
but often leads to little progress.
If you want to reach mastery in a foreign language,
you don't want to waste precious time on ineffective methods.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/bad-advice.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/bad-advice.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 03:51:27 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
