<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
<title>All Japanese All The Time - AJATT</title>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/index.html</link>
<description>Tatsumoto's guide to learning Japanese. How to use Free Software to learn Japanese, and more.</description>
<language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 08:24:32 +0300</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 08:24:32 +0300</pubDate>
<atom:link href="https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Ankidrone decks: Audio issues on iOS</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>I wanted to reach out regarding Ankidrone Essentials V8.
On my computer, all the audio files play without any issues.
However, in Anki Mobile on iOS, many of the audio files do not play.</p>
<p>I tried converting all the OGG files to MP3 to make them compatible,
but I ran into problems.</p>
<p>Do you know if there is a way to make this deck play all the audio files in
Anki Mobile, or does it only work on the computer? Any guidance or solution
would be greatly appreciated.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/ankidrone-decks-audio-issues-on-ios.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/ankidrone-decks-audio-issues-on-ios.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 21:22:47 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Niche proprietary games and AJATT</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>What if a person's motivation for learning Japanese
is only to play niche proprietary games/software
that will never be localized into their native language.
How could they follow the AJATT method?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If someone's only <a href="im-not-motivated-and-dont-enjoy-learning-japanese.html">motivation</a>
is playing a specific set of <a href="are-video-games-good-for-immersion.html">games</a>,
that's a recipe for quitting once they've finished those games.
Try to broaden your content choices so you always have something to do in Japanese.
If you spend too long searching for content,
your immersion is paused and you don't progress.
To succeed with Japanese
you need both <a href="active-immersion.html">active</a> and <a href="passive-immersion.html">passive</a> immersion,
and games alone won't cover everything.</p>
<p>This situation where you have only <a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/proprietary.html">proprietary</a>
options and no <a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html">free</a> alternatives
isn't unique to language learning.
I think <a href="https://stallman.org/">Richard Stallman</a> would say that if there's no libre alternative,
he'd still refuse to run the proprietary version.
From a software-freedom perspective,
not running proprietary software preserves your freedom just as much as running free software.</p>
<p>The GNU Project's philosophy says we should avoid proprietary software.
That said,
Richard Stallman also allowed an <a href="https://www.gnu.org/gnu/thegnuproject.html">exception</a>:
using a proprietary program can be justified if it is crucial to developing
a free replacement that will help others stop using the proprietary program.
So if your goal is to help other AJATTers obtain free replacements for those Japanese games,
you might choose to run them for the purpose of reverse-engineering or creating alternatives.
Running proprietary software solely for immersion is a bad idea.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/proprietary-games-and-ajatt.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/proprietary-games-and-ajatt.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 04:14:50 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>About this site</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>This site contains <a href="whats-ajatt.html">AJATT</a>'s language learning guide and related information.
Here you'll find everything you need to know about learning foreign languages.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/about-this-site.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/about-this-site.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 18:53:39 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Will immersing in certain genres of content for a long time make my speech inappropriate for my identity?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Hi! In the past I have heard other Japanese learners say that women speak
Japanese very differently from men and that learning Japanese purely from
copying slice of life/CGDCT material will make you sound obviously effete and
feminine if you are a male. Is it something to worry about?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes, there are sizable gender differences in Japanese.
Men and women speak and act differently,
use different expressions, pronouns and sentence endings.
People also change how they speak as they age.
A 75-year-old man doesn't sound the same as a 15-year-old girl.
This is true for many other languages as well.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/will-immersion-in-certain-genres-make-my-speech-inappropriate.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/will-immersion-in-certain-genres-make-my-speech-inappropriate.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 12:31:36 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>What's actually the best way to find easy anime?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>What's actually the best way to find easy anime?
You would think just analyzing the subs for speed,
frequency and words you know, maybe even grammar,
would make it possible to rate how easy it will be for you.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>When I learned Japanese,
I didn't worry about categorizing anime into <em>easy</em> VS <em>hard</em>.
The first anime I mined after making my mining deck was Steins;Gate.
Although it isn't the simplest anime if you count the difficulty of every word,
it wasn't hard to mine from it.
I simply went through it line by line,
adding every sentence with unknown words to Anki.</p>
<p>For beginners,
it's fine to start with
<a href="what-good-things-are-there-to-watch-for-a-complete-beginner.html">any slice of life anime</a>
without stressing over the difficulty.</p>
<p>Don't try to mine sentences right from day one.
I only began sentence mining after I had learned more than 1,000 words
<a href="basic-vocabulary.html">from a premade deck</a>.</p>
<p>There are many resources that claim to organize anime by difficulty for Japanese learners.
I think it's best to avoid them.
They often miss the mark,
potentially leading you to anime that isn't interesting or suitable for your level.
Plus,
many of these resources require you to create an account
and come with questionable money-grab schemes.
If you find an anime that looks fun, it's probably the best one for you personally.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/whats-actually-the-best-way-to-find-easy-anime.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/whats-actually-the-best-way-to-find-easy-anime.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 18:22:10 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Should I write each word once or many times while practicing handwriting?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>I printed out some handwriting practice templates.
However,
I haven't found any recommendations on
how many times to write each word when reviewing in Anki.
My question is,
should I write each word only once, or should I practice in batches?
If the latter, how many repetitions should I do per batch?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Write each word once.
You just need to write a word correctly with the correct stroke order.</p>
<p>The goal is to test whether you can recall how to write something from memory.
For example,
if you were to go to Japan and needed to write by hand, you'd want to be prepared.
Although writing a word multiple times in a row might help a little,
the real benefits come from <a href="spaced-repetition.html">spaced repetition</a>.
Waiting before trying to recall a word again is more effective,
which is why <a href="setting-up-anki.html">Anki</a> has learning steps.
Anki takes care of the intervals for you,
and if you forget how to write a word,
the program will show you the corresponding flashcard more often.</p>
<p>For learning handwriting, see <a href="writing-japanese.html#writing-kanji">Writing TSCs</a>.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/should-i-write-each-word-many-times.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/should-i-write-each-word-many-times.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 03:07:10 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Is it worth making production cards?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Is it worth learning words not just by associating a word with its translation,
but also in reverse — from translation to word?
For example,
if I look at a list of translations and try to recall the corresponding Japanese word.
It feels much harder than simply memorizing the translation.
However, this method seems to strengthens my memory.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-worth-making-production-cards.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-worth-making-production-cards.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 04:48:15 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I barely understand anything. Is immersion actually helpful?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Absolutely!</p>
<p>Immersion is crucial for mastering a foreign language.
Your brain is a pattern-recognition machine,
optimized for language learning
and designed to learn languages naturally.
By surrounding yourself with content in the target language (TL),
you begin to internalize vocabulary and grammar intuitively,
even if you don't notice it.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-helpful-to-immerse-if-i-barely-understand.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-helpful-to-immerse-if-i-barely-understand.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 05:06:48 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Classes</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Traditional language classes suck.
They cost money.
They are boring.
And they are not effective.</p>
<p>If you're enrolling in a typical textbook-based Japanese class,
hoping that teachers will magically transfer
<a href="are-textbooks-bad.html">textbook</a> material into your brain
during short daily lessons,
you might want to rethink your strategy.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/classes.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/classes.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 21:17:08 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I Stopped Using Matrix</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>I have some exciting news, folks!
You've been asking me to do this for a long time,
and now the moment has finally arrived.
I've decided to discontinue our Matrix community
in favor of a different platform.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/i-stopped-using-matrix.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/i-stopped-using-matrix.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 20:02:51 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
