<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
<title>Tatsumoto Ren</title>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/index.html</link>
<description>How to use Free Software to learn Japanese, and more.</description>
<language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 12:19:01 +0300</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 12:19:01 +0300</pubDate>
<atom:link href="https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Is it important to practice reading tategaki?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>No, you don't have to practice reading tategaki.</p>
<p>In Japanese, the term tategaki (<code>縦書き</code>) is used to describe text written vertically.
This style of writing is read from top to bottom, then right to left,
and was traditionally the standard for Japanese writing.
However, in modern times,
horizontal writing is more common due to the prevalence of the internet and other digital media.
Modern Japanese people often read both horizontal and vertical text.</p>
<p>You don't have to go out of your way and practice reading text written vertically.
It is not something to be overly concerned about.
As someone learning Japanese,
it is unavoidable to come across vertical text,
just like it's hard to avoid reading text with kanji.
So as long as your <a href="whats-immersion.html">immersion</a> is balanced,
and you regularly read manga or light novels, you're set.
In light novels and manga text is always vertical, maybe with some exceptions.</p>
<p>If you only read on a computer screen,
it is possible that the program you are using to read books shows the text horizontally
and does not support tategaki.
If so, don't worry about it too much,
as manga alone will still provide you with sufficient
practice to become proficient in reading tategaki.</p>
<p>Reading tategaki is not difficult.
I find that reading both vertical and horizontal Japanese is natural,
and there is no difference in terms of difficulty.
Even if you totally avoid media that has tategaki,
it is unlikely to have a major negative impact on your reading ability.
You still will be able to read vertical Japanese text,
much like you can read vertical English text.
Maybe your reading speed will be a bit slower,
but it's not something that trips people off.</p>
<p>Ultimately,
there are more important and challenging aspects of Japanese
that could benefit from focus and deliberate practice.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-important-to-practice-reading-tategaki.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-important-to-practice-reading-tategaki.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 02:24:50 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I'm not a kid anymore. Am I too old to learn a language?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>No matter your age,
it is never too late to learn a new language.
Research and anecdotal evidence have both proven that
adults can acquire languages similarly to how children do it.
In fact, adults aquire languages faster than babies.
The advantage of being an adult
is that we can use various tools and techniques to speed up the process,
such as the AJATT method,
which can typically help one become fluent in a language within just 2 years.
This is a far cry from a typical 4-year-old child who,
despite having been exposed to language input constantly,
still doesn't sound very good and still makes some mistakes.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/im-not-a-kid-anymore-am-i-too-old-to-learn-a-language.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/im-not-a-kid-anymore-am-i-too-old-to-learn-a-language.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 22:08:43 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Pausing. How often should I look things up while actively immersing?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>If you never pause, it means you don't look up words at all.
The more you look up, the faster you progress.
If you have to look up a word in every sentence, it quickly becomes tedious.
So your task is to
try to find the balance between enjoyment and frequent lookups.</p>
<p>You can watch raw and try to understand only through the visuals,
watch with subs and actively look up unknown words,
or do something in between.
When it comes to doing something in between,
it boils down to
looking things up only once every couple minutes.
In, practice, however, I find that most people can't do it.
It's a lot of work to sit with a timer
or somehow arbitrary track time and decide when to look up and when not to look up.
So I recommend splitting your time between media where you look up everything
and media where you don't look up anything.</p>
<p>One of our community members, <code>ﾌｪﾘﾍﾟ</code>, shares the following routine:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I always keep two TV-shows.
One for mining <strong>everything</strong>
and the other one for pure enjoyment, without lookups.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I agree with this.
I never look up when I'm watching <abbr title="movies and TV-shows without any subtitles">raw</abbr>,
and always look up when I'm watching with subtitles.
When reading, I always look up unless I can easily infer the meaning from the context.
But be careful when skipping lookups when reading
because you might run across a word written in kanji
and assume that it is read one way when it is actually read differently.
This is not a problem when reading alongside an audiobook though.</p>
<p>If you find yourself looking up too many unknown bits too often,
switching to easier content is a solution too.
You can go back to the difficult medium once you increase your skill level.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/pausing-how-often-should-i-look-things-up.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/pausing-how-often-should-i-look-things-up.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 06:11:01 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>In order to increase my reading speed, should I force myself to start skimming?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Khatzumoto recommended skimming mostly as a motivational tool.
You skim boring parts to get to the fun parts, and it keeps you focused on your immersion.</p>
<p>When it comes to reading speed, skimming won't help.
If you read a lot, your reading speed will improve naturally.
To increase your reading speed
you need to read at your natural speed, and read a lot.
Slowly over time your natural reading speed will get better.</p>
<p>The more you read, the more your brain will be able to recognize patterns and
group words together. For example, when you first start learning Japanese, you
may need to read each character individually to understand long patterns
such as <code>○○ざるを得ない</code>, <code>○○もさることながら</code> or <code>どちらかと言うと</code>.
But as you become more familiar with the language,
you will be able to recognize longer patterns instantly,
without having to say each syllable in your head.
Your brain will become able to process multiple characters and multiple words as single units.
With practice,
you start to chunk the language into larger and larger pieces.
As you become more accustomed to picking up groups of words as single units,
your reading speed increases due to the decreased number of chunks you have to process.</p>
<p>So the key to being able to read faster naturally
is building the mental infrastructure in your brain.
Forcing yourself to read faster than you are comfortable will not lead to the desired result.
Speed is only achievable through dedicated practice and time.</p>
<p>I don't recommend skimming, as it can lead to missing important information.
It is much more beneficial to be able to actually read and recognize each piece of the text,
rather than just jumping through words,
skipping chunks
and inferring the meaning from the context.
While it can be possible to comprehend and infer the meaning of Japanese text without certain parts,
such as conjugations and particles,
the lack of exposure to essential words and grammar
may impede one's ability to use them when speaking.
For language acquisition
it is important that you pay attention to each bit of information in the text
so that your brain can absorb the patterns and acquire grammar.
Avoid skimming in order to gain maximum exposure to all elements of Japanese.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/to-increase-reading-speed-should-i-start-skimming.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/to-increase-reading-speed-should-i-start-skimming.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 04:47:06 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Is it more efficient to stick to one genre/domain instead of jumping around?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>It's definitely more efficient to focus on one genre or one domain at a time.
But of course you need to take enjoyment into account.
If you stick to one domain for too long then it can become really tedious.</p>
<p>In the guide I said that in the beginning
I recommend immersing in slice of life movies and TV shows.
In slice of life shows you've got a limited range of vocabulary,
and the words that are being used are common across the entire language.
This is the recommended first domain.
Having a solid foundation in the initial domain
makes it much easier to learn new domains.
When you know the most basic vocabulary,
you can move forward really quickly.
You build up a strong base in one domain,
increase your overall comprehension,
and then use that to your advantage as you move on to new domains.</p>
<p>If you focus your attention on a specific domain of your target language,
it will be much easier for your brain to absorb the patterns.
By narrowing your field of study and taking it one domain at a time,
you can ensure that your brain can fully focus on one thing
and master it before moving on to another.
This approach is much more efficient than trying to learn many things at once.</p>
<p>Every time you choose a new genre,
move to a different domain,
it will have a different set of commonly used words and expressions.
Domains can be similar to each other or very different from each other.
Some specialized domains can be quite difficult to understand without lots of study.
Try not to jump to a new domain
that is too distinct from other domains you have immersed in.
Also, try to get a solid foothold in the domain before moving to the next domain.</p>
<p>Once you reach advanced stages,
worrying too much about differences between domains is not going to be productive.
For example,
if in the beginning you're immersing only in slice of life TV shows,
in later stages you don't have to distinguish between anime and reality shows, or anime and dramas.
Moving from one domain to another becomes pretty easy.</p>
<p>If you immerse in only one genre,
you're going to quickly increase your understanding of the content in that genre.
Once you understand a certain genre well,
your overall progress in the language will slow down
until you tackle a new domain.
So, sticking to one genre for too long is also a bad idea,
but jumping between many genres will result in facing too many unknown words
if you're not fluent yet.
Ultimately it's about finding the balance between
trying to master domains of the language in the most efficient way
and immersing in what looks interesting.
Prioritize enjoyment over &quot;efficiency&quot;.
The fun cut to Japanese is almost always the shortcut.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-more-efficient-to-stick-to-one-domain.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-more-efficient-to-stick-to-one-domain.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 00:06:19 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I'm not motivated and don't enjoy learning Japanese, is it still worth my time?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Being unmotivated means that you don't actually want to learn Japanese,
but you want to &quot;want to learn Japanese&quot;.
And if so I highly recommend quitting.</p>
<p>Don't learn Japanese.
It's just honestly stupid.
Just don't.
There's no point to learning Japanese.
There's nothing special about it.
It's completely meaningless.
And that's the honest truth.</p>
<p>Doing Japanese means making a lot of sacrifices.
To get good at Japanese you have to permanently change your life in a certain way.
You have to spend multiple years
reading, watching, listening, looking up words, making flashcards, reviewing flashcards, and so on.
If you hate all of that then it's not going to be worth it for you.
Being fluent in Japanese is not going to make you happy if the process didn't.
And even if it did,
I don't think the result is worth suffering for several years.</p>
<p>When I was learning Japanese,
I never had problems with motivation.
I had a concrete goal.
I knew that I wanted to understand untranslated anime.
Before I started Japanese, I had been watching anime for 7 years,
so I simply pegged learning Japanese to an existing habit.
I was going to watch anime almost every day anyway,
so why not do it in Japanese.</p>
<p>You have to have a strong passion about something in Japan or about Japanese.
Otherwise, it's not going to work.
Instead of <em>learning Japanese</em> enjoy Japanese because it's there.
Read this book, watch this movie, read this manga, listen to this song.
Play the short games.</p>
<p>Now, if you had motivation before, but lost it,
that's a slightly different problem.
You've probably lost your goal.
You need to rediscover it, or find a new one.
What do you want to do in Japanese?
Have you watched every movie there is to watch?
Have you read every book there is to read?
There's no magic pill for fixing motivation,
but there's lots of fun things to do in the language.
Do Japanese because it's fun.</p>
<p>Lastly,
think back to when you didn't know anything at all.
It's important to appreciate how far you have come,
how much you have learned,
and how much you already know.
You have already made it this far, and you can continue to make more progress.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/im-not-motivated-and-dont-enjoy-learning-japanese.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/im-not-motivated-and-dont-enjoy-learning-japanese.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 21:50:02 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I am struggling to switch from English to Japanese media. Should I go cold turkey?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>You shouldn't have this problem.
Most people before they start AJATT
already have a passion for otaku content
like anime, manga, ranobe,
or other types of Japanese media.
For them learning Japanese is a means to
get more enjoyment out of the media they are fond of.
If you decided to learn Japanese out of the blue,
and you don't like any of the above,
it's going to be very hard to immerse without quitting and going back to English.</p>
<p>If you like anime, there will be no temptation to watch crap in English.
Anime exists only in Japanese.
Most of the stuff people like in Japanese has no alternatives in the English world.
So you can either consume translated media which is always worse,
or you can learn Japanese and experience the original to its fullest.
A lot of stuff isn't even translated, and isn't going to be.</p>
<p>Find something you like in Japanese.
Try to discover new stuff,
something that has no alternatives in English.
I feel like most people reading this already have an answer.</p>
<p>If you look at this from the opposite side, there's no difference.
Let's say you're Japanese, and you're learning English.
There is unique, interesting English content.
You just have to find it, find what you like.</p>
<p>When it comes to should you go cold turkey,
you can't do it until you find media you're passionate about.
When you do, I bet you're going to jump cold turkey without a second thought.
If you don't find unique and compelling content,
immersion will feel like study,
like going to classes,
and your willpower is not going to last long.</p>
<p>If there's English media that interest you,
it's okay if you do English once or twice a week on schedule.
If you do only Japanese,
you will be constantly craving the English media you used to consume.
There's a chance that you end up losing to the temptation,
dropping Japanese immersion
and going back to all the English content you've been abstaining from.
It will be worse than occasional breaks.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/i-am-struggling-to-switch-from-english-to-japanese-media.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/i-am-struggling-to-switch-from-english-to-japanese-media.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 21:52:55 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How much reading is required to counteract not SRSing?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>You can't fully counteract not SRSing.
This is true for every use case of the SRS,
especially when learning things like math, programming, physics, anatomy, biochemistry, etc.
In language learning it is less noticeable,
which leads to the idea that one can stop SRSing and experience no negative effects.
This idea is more common among language learners.</p>
<p>Now,
if you learn a language to some level of proficiency,
and then stop using it completely,
including immersion and the SRS,
one day you'll forget all of it.
If you immerse a little, it will happen later.
If you immerse a lot, you will be improving.
This all is pretty obvious.
Nonetheless,
language consists of <a href="how-broad-or-narrow-is-a-domain-of-language.html">domains</a> of various sizes.
Much like if you go to a math class,
learn something,
and then stop contacting or using that information,
you will forget it,
without the SRS you have to regularly come back to every domain you've immersed with,
or you'll forget vocabulary specific to that domain.</p>
<p>There are many corner-case words that could be easily lost without repetition.
These are words that come up maybe just a few times a year or less.
Things like names of different
animals, plants, food, fish and birds, stars and planets;
words related to various skills,
fields science and art;
and many more.
It's true that they are not very important,
but they still come up occasionally.
Every time they come up, you're going to feel like you're a child who's lost.</p>
<p>The SRS is the reason why AJATTers can have passive vocabulary
larger than an average native their age.
They're able to surpass natives in 5-7 years.
A native speaker has spent their entire life using the language.
When you take out the SRS,
you start forgetting words you don't run into often enough,
and as a result it takes you way longer to catch up to a native.
Without enough immersion every day you may never be able to do it.</p>
<p>That's why it's not possible to counteract not SRSing —
there are too many domains to worry about.
Even if you read all day, there's always some vocabulary you're not contacting.
When you stop using the SRS,
the rules change,
and you enter the game of fighting a leaking bucket.
The SRS becomes especially important
when there's not enough repetition of any kind of information.</p>
<p>Khatzumoto has an article on this topic,
<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20111019215213/http://www.alljapaneseallthetime.com/blog/khatz-if-youre-fluent-why-do-you-still-srs">If You’re Fluent, Why Do You Still SRS</a>.
In the article he says that once he stopped SRSing,
he started forgetting words that normally you don't see very often,
words that you maybe don't see every day but need once in a while.
Khatz was frustrated with his inability to improve without the SRS,
so he started SRSing again.</p>
<p>Throughout my Japanese learning journey I always knew the consequences of dropping the SRS
from reading about what people before me, including Khatz, experienced,
so I never stopped SRSing.
Once you've used SRS for a while,
you start applying it to all aspects of your life,
not just language learning.
You start SRSing your exams, for example.
When you have a variety of different topics in your SRS,
it becomes harder to quit it.</p>
<p>If you have too many due cards each day,
consider <a href="setting-up-anki.html#options-groups">optimizing your settings</a>
and <a href="how-to-review.html#card-retirement">retiring mature cards</a>.
You could even delete some decks that you're sure you don't need anymore,
though I'm not a fan of deleting entire decks.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-much-reading-is-required-to-counteract-not-srsing.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-much-reading-is-required-to-counteract-not-srsing.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 11:07:55 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I only do passive immersion and things aren't working, what's wrong?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>The answer is obvious. Do active immersion.</p>
<p>Even if you have headphones on all day,
without active immersion you can't expect any improvement.
The whole point of passive immersion
is to get additional exposure to the sentences you already have learned to some extent.</p>
<p>Especially in early stages
during passive immersion
you generally consume exactly the same content
that you learn from during active immersion.
During passive immersion your brain should be exposed to what you've been working on actively.
If you're doing only passive listening,
your brain is going to filter the information out as background noise.</p>
<p>During active immersion
you need to give your full attention to the immersion
and try to understand as much as possible.
Make flashcards for the unknown bits.
Then, when you're going to re-listen to the same content passively,
listening is going to help you solidify the knowledge.</p>
<p>Passive immersion only helps to the extent that you are also doing active immersion.
If you skip active immersion,
you won't understand what's going on.
But if you listen to familiar content,
it is easier to follow the story.
Even if your attention moves to something else,
when you move it back,
you can still understand what's going on because you already know the plot.</p>
<p>It is possible to learn a language without passive immersion,
but it is almost impossible to do without active immersion.
You need to actively immerse and look up as many words as you can while doing so.</p>
<p>If you do no active immersion,
passive immersion does little to nothing.
If you are doing lots of active immersion each day,
then passive immersion starts to become very beneficial.</p>
<p>So what I recommend everyone to do is
watch anime, movies and dramas actively
and then put each episode through <a href="passive-listening.html#impd">impd</a> to get condensed audio.
Listen to the condensed audio in the background until <code>impd</code> archives it.
The process should not require much time,
you only need time to watch a few episodes every day.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/i-only-do-passive-immersion-and-things-arent-working-whats-wrong.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/i-only-do-passive-immersion-and-things-arent-working-whats-wrong.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 07:50:27 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How to learn readings after finishing isolated kanji study?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Through <a href="discussing-various-card-templates.html#targeted-sentence-cards">targeted sentence cards</a>.</p>
<p>Various methods of <a href="learning-kanji.html#isolated-kanji-study">isolated kanji study</a>
usually don't cover kanji readings.
If they do, they have you learn the most common reading,
as KanjiDamage does, for example.
Knowing the most common reading helps a little,
but you still need to learn how to read actual words you come across by yourself.</p>
<p>After you're done with isolated kanji study,
learn kanji readings in context.
Readings should not be learned in isolation.
You're going to learn words and their readings at the same time.
So what you need to do is
read a lot of native Japanese content, look up words and make TSCs.</p>
<p>At first, you may want to use a premade deck.
I recommend downloading
<a href="basic-vocabulary.html">Ankidrone Starter Pack</a>
and learning from 1,000 to 3,000 cards from it.
The deck has Japanese sentences on the front,
English translations on the back.
It also comes with native audio.
You learn what the words mean and how to read them.</p>
<p>So you learn each word by itself,
as a single unit,
and over time your ability to predict kanji readings becomes stronger.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-to-learn-readings-after-finishing-isolated-kanji-study.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-to-learn-readings-after-finishing-isolated-kanji-study.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 02:20:51 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
