<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
<title>Tatsumoto's guide to learning Japanese</title>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/index.html</link>
<description>How to use Free Software to learn Japanese, and more.</description>
<language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 12:32:26 +0300</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 12:32:26 +0300</pubDate>
<atom:link href="https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Will immersing in certain genres of content for a long time make my speech inappropriate for my identity?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Hi! In the past I have heard other Japanese learners say that women speak
Japanese very differently from men and that learning Japanese purely from
copying slice of life/CGDCT material will make you sound obviously effete and
feminine if you are a male. Is it something to worry about?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes, there are sizable gender differences in Japanese.
Men and women speak and act differently,
use different expressions, pronouns and sentence endings.
People also change how they speak as they age.
A 75-year-old man doesn't sound the same as a 15-year-old girl.
This is true for many other languages as well.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/will-immersion-in-certain-genres-make-my-speech-inappropriate.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/will-immersion-in-certain-genres-make-my-speech-inappropriate.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 12:31:36 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>What's actually the best way to find easy anime?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>What's actually the best way to find easy anime?
You would think just analyzing the subs for speed,
frequency and words you know, maybe even grammar,
would make it possible to rate how easy it will be for you.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>When I learned Japanese,
I didn't worry about categorizing anime into <em>easy</em> VS <em>hard</em>.
The first anime I mined after making my mining deck was Steins;Gate.
Although it isn't the simplest anime if you count the difficulty of every word,
it wasn't hard to mine from it.
I simply went through it line by line,
adding every sentence with unknown words to Anki.</p>
<p>For beginners,
it's fine to start with
<a href="what-good-things-are-there-to-watch-for-a-complete-beginner.html">any slice of life anime</a>
without stressing over the difficulty.</p>
<p>Don't try to mine sentences right from day one.
I only began sentence mining after I had learned more than 1,000 words
<a href="basic-vocabulary.html">from a premade deck</a>.</p>
<p>There are many resources that claim to organize anime by difficulty for Japanese learners.
I think it's best to avoid them.
They often miss the mark,
potentially leading you to anime that isn't interesting or suitable for your level.
Plus,
many of these resources require you to create an account
and come with questionable money-grab schemes.
If you find an anime that looks fun, it's probably the best one for you personally.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/whats-actually-the-best-way-to-find-easy-anime.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/whats-actually-the-best-way-to-find-easy-anime.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 18:22:10 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Should I write each word once or many times while practicing handwriting?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>I printed out some handwriting practice templates.
However,
I haven't found any recommendations on
how many times to write each word when reviewing in Anki.
My question is,
should I write each word only once, or should I practice in batches?
If the latter, how many repetitions should I do per batch?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Write each word once.
You just need to write a word correctly with the correct stroke order.</p>
<p>The goal is to test whether you can recall how to write something from memory.
For example,
if you were to go to Japan and needed to write by hand, you'd want to be prepared.
Although writing a word multiple times in a row might help a little,
the real benefits come from <a href="spaced-repetition.html">spaced repetition</a>.
Waiting before trying to recall a word again is more effective,
which is why <a href="setting-up-anki.html">Anki</a> has learning steps.
Anki takes care of the intervals for you,
and if you forget how to write a word,
the program will show you the corresponding flashcard more often.</p>
<p>For learning handwriting, see <a href="writing-japanese.html#writing-kanji">Writing TSCs</a>.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/should-i-write-each-word-many-times.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/should-i-write-each-word-many-times.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 03:07:10 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Is it worth making production cards?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Is it worth learning words not just by associating a word with its translation,
but also in reverse — from translation to word?
For example,
if I look at a list of translations and try to recall the corresponding Japanese word.
It feels much harder than simply memorizing the translation.
However, this method seems to strengthens my memory.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-worth-making-production-cards.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-worth-making-production-cards.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 04:48:15 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I barely understand anything. Is immersion actually helpful?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Absolutely!</p>
<p>Immersion is crucial for mastering a foreign language.
Your brain is a pattern-recognition machine,
optimized for language learning
and designed to learn languages naturally.
By surrounding yourself with content in the target language (TL),
you begin to internalize vocabulary and grammar intuitively,
even if you don't notice it.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-helpful-to-immerse-if-i-barely-understand.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-helpful-to-immerse-if-i-barely-understand.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 05:06:48 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Classes</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Traditional language classes suck.
They cost money.
They are boring.
And they are not effective.</p>
<p>If you're enrolling in a typical textbook-based Japanese class,
hoping that teachers will magically transfer
<a href="are-textbooks-bad.html">textbook</a> material into your brain
during short daily lessons,
you might want to rethink your strategy.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/classes.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/classes.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 21:17:08 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>I Stopped Using Matrix</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>I have some exciting news, folks!
You've been asking me to do this for a long time,
and now the moment has finally arrived.
I've decided to discontinue our Matrix community
in favor of a different platform.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/i-stopped-using-matrix.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/i-stopped-using-matrix.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 20:02:51 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How much time should I spend studying basic grammar each day?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>It's up to you,
but we recommend spending around 15 to 30 minutes each day on <a href="learning-grammar.html">grammar</a>.
We all know that reading about grammar isn't exactly the most exciting thing in the world.
Thus,
we think that consuming grammar theory <strong>incrementally</strong> over time
will make it easier to consolidate and integrate what you've learned.</p>
<p>If you choose to spend about 30 minutes a day studying grammar,
it's perfectly fine to study basic grammar alongside
<a href="jp1k-anki-deck.html">Ankidrone Foundation</a>
and/or
<a href="ankidrone-essentials.html">Ankidrone Essentials</a>.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-much-time-should-i-spend-studying-basic-grammar-each-day.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-much-time-should-i-spend-studying-basic-grammar-each-day.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 18:55:53 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Is watching anime with JP subtitles considered as reading?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Yes, it is.
Watching anime with
<a href="mining-from-movies-and-tv-shows.html#obtain-subtitles">Japanese subtitles</a>
counts as reading immersion
because reading the subtitles creates an inner voice
that competes with the spoken language that you're listening to.
As a result,
you are not fully paying attention to the native speech.
Instead,
you focus on your internal subvocalization while reading the subtitles.</p>
<p>If you watched anime with English subtitles before starting to learn Japanese,
you've likely spent thousands of hours listening to native Japanese.
However,
if reading subtitles did not interfere with your listening practice,
you would have already learned the language.
This is why we say that watching with subtitles counts as reading immersion.
When you read subtitles,
your own subvocalization interferes with and overshadows the audio.
Consequently,
you end up learning the language of the subtitles
rather than the language of the audio.
In this case, the language of the English fansubs.</p>
<p>Watching anime with Japanese subtitles can help you notice and learn more words,
but it will cause your listening skills to
<a href="is-it-harmful-to-always-have-tl-subtitles-on.html">lag behind</a>.
Relying too heavily on subtitles can create a crutch,
making it difficult to transition to listening without any text support.
If you've spent a long time watching anime with Japanese subtitles
and neglected listening practice,
you will be frustrated when you decide to turn off the subs and watch raw anime.
While you can improve your listening skills by going cold turkey
and immersing with a lot of raw anime,
it will be challenging at first.
It's better to
<a href="how-do-you-recommend-starting-on-listening-practice.html">train your listening ability</a>
while you're still a beginner.
Therefore,
AJATT recommends prioritizing listening to avoid this issue.</p>
<p>We recommend disabling subtitles if you don't need them.
For those who need them,
enable them only when you don't understand something.
Keeping them visible creates a hindrance,
and you can't help but read the subs even if it's unintentional.
It's <a href="en-and-ja-subs-at-the-same-time.html">difficult to ignore</a> them completely.</p>
<p>So,
regardless of your current skill level,
when we <a href="how-should-i-divide-my-study-time.html">divide our study time</a>,
watching something with TL subs counts toward your reading time.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-watching-anime-with-jp-subtitles-considered-as-reading.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-watching-anime-with-jp-subtitles-considered-as-reading.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 07:02:17 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Can't I just read a textbook? Are textbooks inherently bad?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto Ren</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>If you seriously want to master your target language,
textbooks are not for you.
We recommend skipping them entirely and learning the language through immersion.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/are-textbooks-bad.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/are-textbooks-bad.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto Ren</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 22:00:04 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
