<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel><title>Tatsumoto Ren</title><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/index.html</link>
<description>How to use Free Software to learn Japanese, and more.</description><language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 13:58:41 +0300</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 13:58:41 +0300</pubDate>
<atom:link href="https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item><title>
JLPT Tango N1 Anki deck</title><description><![CDATA[
<p align="center">
<img src="img/tango_n1.webp" alt="cover" style="max-height: 400px;">
</p>
<p>3000 Essential Vocabulary for the JLPT N1,
also known as JLPT Tango N1,
is a textbook to prepare for the JLPT N1.
It contains ~2000 Japanese sentences and their English translations.
The book includes vocabulary found commonly on the JLPT and often used in everyday life.</p>
<p>With the help of our chat members,
we have created an Anki deck from
sentences listed in the book
and native audio that comes with it.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/jlpt-tango-n1-anki-deck.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/jlpt-tango-n1-anki-deck.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2022 21:51:14 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Learning grammar</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>What's grammar?
Should you learn grammar?
How to learn grammar?
Let's answer these question in this article.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/learning-grammar.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/learning-grammar.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 05:55:16 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Immersion with YouTube</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>YouTube is a popular website where people can upload and watch videos.
Through watching YouTube you can immerse with native Japanese content.
Such content can be of particular interest to people
who want to understand colloquial Japanese,
speech with a lot of mumbling, slurs and slang.
There are many language-dense streams and podcasts on YouTube
that can be used for background listening.
You can also find news channels with more formal speech.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/immersion-with-youtube.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/immersion-with-youtube.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 17:32:30 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Understanding monolingual definitions</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>A typical entry in a monolingual dictionary looks similar to this:</p>
<pre><code>あした [3] 【明日・朝】 （名）
（１）今日の次の日。
（２）夜が終わって，明るくなった時。あさ。
</code></pre>
<p>Every dictionary usually has its own, unique system of notation.
On this page I primarily use <code>大辞泉</code> as an example.
If you need help finding monolingual dictionaries, see the
<a href="resources.html#dictionaries">Dictionaries</a> resources section.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/understanding-monolingual-definitions.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/understanding-monolingual-definitions.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:45:48 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
How to type in Japanese</title><description><![CDATA[
<p align="center">
<img alt="Japanese keyboard" src="img/keyboard.webp" style="width: 400px;">
</p>
<p>Ever wondered how Japanese people type?
No one knows the answer.
Some people say that they use huge keyboards with hundreds of keys like on the picture.
Luckily for us, we don't have to imitate Japanese people and buy a keyboard like that.
There are programs called <strong>Input Method Editors</strong> (IMEs)
that help us do the same thing on a regular computer keyboard.
With an IME you type Latin letters
and the software automatically converts them to Japanese characters.</p>
<p>Typing words in a dictionary,
searching the web
or talking to people who pretend to be Japanese on the Internet
all require being able to input Japanese characters.
If you're serious about learning Japanese,
you need to learn how to do it.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-to-type-in-japanese.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-to-type-in-japanese.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 12:34:47 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
JLPT Tango N2 Anki deck</title><description><![CDATA[
<p align="center">
<img src="img/tango_n2.webp" alt="cover" style="max-height: 400px;">
</p>
<p>2500 Essential Vocabulary for the JLPT N2,
also known as JLPT Tango N2,
is a textbook to prepare for the JLPT N2.
It contains ~1,500 Japanese sentences and their English translations.
The book includes vocabulary found commonly on the JLPT and often used in everyday life.</p>
<p>With the help of our chat members,
we have created an Anki deck specifically for the JLPT Tango N2.
We took sentences from the book,
downloaded audio from the publisher's website
and combined them to make this Anki deck.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/jlpt-tango-n2-anki-deck.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/jlpt-tango-n2-anki-deck.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 00:13:57 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Sentence mining</title><description><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Sentence mining</strong> is a process of extracting sentences
that contain unknown words
from the content you read, watch or listen to in your target language
and adding them to Anki in a form of targeted sentence cards (TSCs).
You put an example sentence in the question field
and the definitions, pictures and pronunciations in the answer field.</p>
<p>Sentence mining and immersion are the two most important components of our method.
Immersion provides you with new vocabulary to be mined,
and mined sentences become fuel that advances your language learning.</p>
<p>Finding your own sentences is much more fun than learning from a premade deck,
or, god forbid, a textbook.
Because you're creating Anki cards out of vocabulary found in your immersion,
you're always learning what is relevant to you.
Once you reach this stage, it is way harder to quit Japanese,
as the foundation is already in place.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/sentence-mining.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/sentence-mining.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 23:15:48 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Retiming subtitles</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Japanese subtitles can be found in
<a href="resources.html#japanese-subtitles">many places</a>.
Often after downloading an archive with subtitles for your show
you find that the subtitles are not in sync with the video files you have on your computer.
In this article let's discuss what you can do to sync them.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/retiming-subtitles.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/retiming-subtitles.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 21:32:55 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Setting up Qolibri</title><description><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/qolibri/">Qolibri</a>
is a Qt-based dictionary viewer.
It lets you search multiple dictionaries at one time
so for every word you look up you immediately get multiple definitions.
Qolibri remains one of the most widely used Japanese dictionary viewers for GNU/Linux.</p>
<p>By itself, Qolibri is just a viewer.
To utilize it, you need <strong>dictionary files</strong>.
The dictionary files Qolibri reads are called <a href="https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/EPWING">EPWING</a>s.
EPWING (electronic publishing WING) is a dictionary format
that was allegedly utilized in portable electronic dictionaries.</p>
<p>Qolibri is much better than Yomichan at searching a big number of dictionaries at the same time.
If you try to use more than 5 dictionaries with Yomichan,
it quickly becomes very cluttered and hard to navigate.
Qolibri lists all dictionaries you have on a sidebar.
It is easy to jump between them if you need to.</p>
<p>If you haven't started using Japanese to Japanese dictionaries yet,
feel free to skip this article for now.
Though Japanese to English dictionaries for Qolibri exist, their number is not very large.
The main reason you want to use the program is to browse monolingual dictionaries.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/setting-up-qolibri.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/setting-up-qolibri.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 05:10:24 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
One target sentences</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Let's define a &quot;target&quot; as any unknown piece of information
in a given sentence in a foreign language.
It can be either a word or a grammar structure.
We can divide all sentences we encounter while immersing in our target language into three groups:</p>
<ol>
<li><code>0T</code>, zero-target.
Sentences that don't contain anything you don't already know.</li>
<li><code>1T</code>, one-target.
Sentences that contain one unknown piece of information.</li>
<li><code>2T+</code>, <code>MT</code>, multi-target.
Sentences that contain multiple unknown pieces of information.</li>
</ol>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/one-target-sentences.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/one-target-sentences.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 00:04:36 +0300</pubDate></item>
</channel></rss>
