<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel><title>Tatsumoto Ren</title><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/index.html</link>
<description>How to use Free Software to learn Japanese, and more.</description><language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 08:13:36 +0300</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 08:13:36 +0300</pubDate>
<atom:link href="https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item><title>
Learning Kanji</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Unlike kana which you can learn in a matter of few days no matter what method you pick,
learning kanji is apparently more difficult, and there are many methods of doing it.</p>
<p>To pick the right method
you have to understand why you want to learn kanji in the first place.
The &quot;practice how you play&quot; principle applies here as well.
Kanji do not exist in a vacuum, instead they're used to writing Japanese words,
so in order to &quot;learn&quot; them all you need to do is learn words.
To learn a word means to memorize how it's read and what it means.
Over time as you keep learning words you unconsciously get better at recognizing the kanji.</p>
<p>We advise against learning kanji readings in isolation.
Very often a kanji character has a number of completely different readings.
Not only learning all of them is an enormous task,
but it's impossible to apply the knowledge to real native content when reading.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/learning-kanji.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/learning-kanji.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 06:53:51 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Resources</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>This is the Ajatt-Tools Resources List.
With the help of our community we've gathered the links to help you in your Japanese studies.
We prioritize libre software and content that you can download for free.
Everyone is welcome to suggest more resources in our chat.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/resources.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/resources.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 21:26:34 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Foreword</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Congratulations! You've taken your first step towards learning Japanese!</p>
<p>I'm Tatsumoto. I'm primarily known for a <a href="https://t.me/ajatt_tools">Telegram channel</a>
with focus on helping foreigners learn Japanese language.</p>
<p>This site is a quickstart guide for the subscribers
and anyone who wants to build a solid understanding of the Japanese language.
We focus on understanding before speaking, or input before output.
We believe doing so is the shortest path to fluency,
because you avoid whole groups of problems that come with premature output,
such as foreign accent and grammar mistakes.
This approach makes the journey easy and fun
because from day one you are encouraged to learn from compelling content
made for native speakers of your target language.
Most people who persevered and reached fluency
watched their favorite TV shows in Japanese
and read lots of books and manga every day.
No amount of brute force can get you there,
so forget about traditional approaches such as taking classes or hiring a tutor.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/foreword.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/foreword.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2021 02:38:26 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Setting up Yomichan</title><description><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://foosoft.net/projects/yomichan/">Yomichan</a> is a browser extension
with a pop up dictionary
that allows you to look up unknown words with the hover of a mouse.
On top of that Yomichan can be set up to create Anki cards from the words which you look up.</p>
<p>The process of picking sentences from your immersion
and making Anki cards is called <em>sentence-mining</em> or <em>sentence-picking</em>.
Each mined sentence has to contain one unknown piece of information,
which is referred to as <em>target word</em>.</p>
<p>You don't necessarily have to pick an entire sentence,
but if you're a TSC user it is not necessary to keep mined items short.
When you're out in the wild picking sentences, select the ones that are interesting to you.
Your goal is not to mine every word.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/setting-up-yomichan.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/setting-up-yomichan.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2021 02:24:07 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Donating to Tatsumoto</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Because almost all my content and the tools I make are offered free of charge
the Ajatt-Tools project relies on donations to stay alive.
We do not have ads or privacy-violating trackers, we are entirely dependent on you.</p>
<p>If this site or our free software projects were useful to you,
I'll appreciate if you donate to the Ajatt-Tools maintenance fund
to help me support myself and continue working on Ajatt-Tools.</p>
<h2><a class="anchor" id="patreon" href="#patreon" title="Permanent link"><svg aria-hidden="true" class="aal_svg" height="16" version="1.1" viewBox="0 0 16 16" width="16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path></svg></a>Patreon</h2>
<p>You can support me over at Patreon by clicking the button below.</p>
<p align="center">
    <a target="_blank" href="https://www.patreon.com/bePatron?u=43555128">
        <img alt="patreon" src="img/become_a_patron_button.png">
    </a>
</p>
<h2><a class="anchor" id="monero" href="#monero" title="Permanent link"><svg aria-hidden="true" class="aal_svg" height="16" version="1.1" viewBox="0 0 16 16" width="16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path></svg></a>Monero</h2>
<p>Monero is considered a privacy-focused cryptocurrency, the transactions are all hidden.
There are many ways you can buy or sell Monero, one of the simplest ones is through
<a href="https://changenow.io/">ChangeNow.io</a>.</p>
<pre><code>47sD7pSagHF7mp41SwrDj4KF8dSj4kdK6YUZ9fkmnR8h587wVc1kW66iJy9m83maVjWXtDJxmCVxdieMyGZNFHZ2Fifrbr5
</code></pre>
<p align="center"><img alt="XMR QR" src="img/xmr_qr.png"></p>
<p align="center"><i>XMR QR</i></p>
<p>Thank you very much for your support!</p>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/donating-to-tatsumoto.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/donating-to-tatsumoto.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 20:58:53 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Passive listening</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>When we talk about immersion, we usually divide it into active and passive.
<em>Active immersion</em> requires full attention to the content
and can be practiced through reading and watching content in the target language.
<em>Passive immersion</em> means listening to the language while in idle activities.
When listening passively you're not fully focused on the content,
instead you're doing something else
while having the speech in your target language play in the background.</p>
<p>We do passive immersion during times in a day where we can't actively engage with the language,
such as when cooking, cleaning or commuting.
Although your attention is divided during passive immersion,
because you're left with no other choice,
it is still better compared to no immersion at all.</p>
<p>As noted in the introduction article, there are countless opportunities
to do passive listening throughout the day.
Make passive listening a habit.
Every moment of your life has to be spent interacting with Japanese.</p>
<p>In the beginning passive immersion doesn't contribute much to comprehension gains,
instead it helps start distinguishing sounds and phonemes of your target language.
Focus your attention on hearing the sounds.
Maybe at first you won't even be able to hear where one word ends and another one starts,
but expect passive listening to boost your phonetic awareness within the first months,
given that you combine it with active immersion.</p>
<p>Passive listening is one of the key components of the AJATT method,
so it is important to make it as convenient as possible.
If preparing immersion content is tedious, you are not going to do it.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/passive-listening.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/passive-listening.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 02:08:00 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Mining from manga</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>When we read manga,
sometimes there's a need to quickly OCR a portion of the screen
to look up new words and add sentences to Anki.
To do so, you're going to use an optical character recognition program and a few helper tools.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/mining-from-manga.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/mining-from-manga.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 10:08:10 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Table of Contents</title><description><![CDATA[
<ul>
<li><a href="foreword.html">Foreword</a></li>
<li><a href="introduction-to-learning-japanese.html">Introduction to learning Japanese</a></li>
<li>Setup<ul>
<li><a href="setting-up-anki.html">Anki</a></li>
<li><a href="useful-anki-add-ons-for-japanese.html">Anki add-ons</a></li>
<li><a href="discussing-various-card-templates.html">Card templates</a></li>
<li><a href="setting-up-yomichan.html">Yomichan</a></li>
<li><a href="yomichan-and-epwing-dictionaries.html">Dictionaries</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Basics<ul>
<li><a href="learning-kana-in-two-days.html">Kana</a></li>
<li><a href="learning-kanji.html">Kanji</a></li>
<li><a href="jp1k-anki-deck.html">Kanji Anki deck</a></li>
<li><a href="basic-vocabulary.html">Basic vocabulary</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Tools and card creation<ul>
<li><a href="our-immersion-learning-toolset.html">Our immersion learning toolset</a></li>
<li><a href="passive-listening.html">Passive listening</a></li>
<li><a href="mining-from-manga.html">Manga</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Ajatt-Tools/mpvacious">Movies and TV-shows</a> *</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Ajatt-Tools/autosubsync-mpv">Subtitle Re-sync</a> *</li>
<li><a href="writing-japanese.html">Writing by hand</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Contact and Support<ul>
<li><a href="join-our-community.html">Join our community</a></li>
<li><a href="donating-to-tatsumoto.html">Support</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="resources.html">List of resources</a></li>
</ul>
<p>* To be updated.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href='tag_guide.html'>guide</a></p>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/table-of-contents.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/table-of-contents.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 04:10:54 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Writing Japanese</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>After you've got a few thousand hours of input
and can read content made for natives relatively effortlessly
it makes sense to start practicing writing Japanese by hand.
Bear in mind that being able to do so is not necessary unless you plan to live in Japan.
Nowadays writing is done on a keyboard
and doesn't require recalling characters from memory.
However, writing practice has the potential to improve your overall reading ability.</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="write japanese" src="img/write_japanese.webp"></p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/writing-japanese.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/writing-japanese.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 21:19:48 +0300</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Introduction to learning Japanese</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>The
<a href="http://www.alljapaneseallthetime.com/blog/all-japanese-all-the-time-ajatt-how-to-learn-japanese-on-your-own-having-fun-and-to-fluency/">AJATT site</a>
is great. One thing it is bad at, however,
is telling up to date information about technology and tools one may use.
I've got you covered on the
<a href="our-immersion-learning-toolset.html">tools</a>, <strong>and more</strong>.</p>
<p>Below is a quick rundown of a typical Japanese learning journey
that should get you to basic fluency in less than two years.</p>
<hr>
]]></description><link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/introduction-to-learning-japanese.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/introduction-to-learning-japanese.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 13:37:07 +0300</pubDate></item>
</channel></rss>
