<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
<title>Tatsumoto Ren</title>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/index.html</link>
<description>How to use Free Software to learn Japanese, and more.</description>
<language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 05:06:11 +0300</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 05:06:11 +0300</pubDate>
<atom:link href="https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>What's the best way to make use of an iTalki teacher?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>I'm beginning to utilize iTalki.
many iTalki teachers seem open to structuring a game plan based on what each student requests.
What would you consider to be the most effective use of iTalki
in a way that's complementary to the AJATT philosophy?
What would you personally look for in a teacher?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't know much about iTalki, so I went to their website
and was surprised to see that it doesn't work with JavaScript disabled.
Truly a disappointment.
I couldn't press half of the buttons on the webpage,
all I could do is read the text on the few pages that were able to load.</p>
<p>So apparently Italki is a platform where you pay to have lessons with language teachers.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>英語 のスキルが確実に向上する方法をお探しですか？
italki には資格を持つ 英語 講師が在籍しています。
英語 のオンライン講師のレッスンを受けて、英語 力アップを目指しましょう。</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the world of language learning,
paying for speaking practice is often compared to paying for sex.
So you're about to do something really shameful there.
I do not think that iTalki can be utilized in a way that aligns with the AJATT philosophy.
AJATT has always been about learning by yourself,
and on this website I also stress it a lot.
Ask yourself,
would another native speaker of your native language
pay you to have a conversation with you?
Would you pay a native speaker of your native language to have a conversation with you?
Probably not, right?
The reason some people are paid to speak is that what they say is of value.
Famous businessmen, scientists, programmers, politicians are paid to
give talks and lectures
because they share valuable knowledge,
not because they speak a certain language.
The value of a conversation lies in its content, not simply in the act of speaking a language.
Having a meaningless conversation in another language
with a language teacher is the antithesis of value.
A teacher's role is to teach learners how to learn by themselves,
and thanks to this site you already know how to learn your target language through self-study,
so you don't need to pay anybody.</p>
<p>If you are &quot;looking for a way to improve&quot; your target language,
you need to understand that
language is a tool for acquiring knowledge.
Speaking is merely a byproduct and a result of acquiring knowledge, not the end goal.
Output ability emerges as a result of listening, watching and reading for thousands of hours.
It is through input that learners acquire the necessary linguistic structures,
vocabulary, grammar,
and cultural context to communicate effectively in the target language.
Therefore, it is crucial to prioritize comprehension over production, input over output.
The best way to improve is by <a href="whats-immersion.html">immersing</a> in the authentic content
made for native speakers of the TL.
Immersion plus <a href="spaced-repetition.html">SRS</a> leads to comprehension ability.
Immersion plus comprehension leads to speaking ability.
Then, speaking ability plus speaking practice leads to speaking mastery.</p>
<p>Before you concern yourself with improving your speaking skills,
you need to make sure that you have mastered understanding your TL.
To be able to speak a foreign language well, you need to be able to hear well.
Pronunciation comes from listening.
If you can't hear it, you can't say it.
If you are able to understand everything you hear, you will be able to speak well.
In addition, a good grasp of the language's phonetics and pitch accent is vital.
Lastly,
research the topic you want to discuss and learn how native speakers converse about it.
You can't talk about something if you don't know how and what to say.
For example, you learn about history of Japan, and then you can talk about it.
Or you learn about Japanese food, and then you can talk about it.
To learn how to talk about something
you need to read and listen to native speakers of your target language.</p>
<p>Speaking practice can be counterproductive.
It is not uncommon for learners to <a href="early-output-or-reading-ahead-of-listening.html">start speaking early</a>
before fully developing their listening abilities
and intuitive understanding of language structures.
This can lead to the reinforcement of incorrect pronunciation and grammar,
and can actually hinder language learning progress.</p>
<p>Let's say you have immersed for <a href="mass-immersion.html">10,000 hours</a>,
and now you are ready to start improving your speaking.
Getting better at speaking requires speaking practice.
Speaking practice is mainly a tool for improving pronunciation.
First,
determine if dedicating time to this activity aligns with your objectives.
After 10,000 hours of immersion,
most individuals can speak proficiently
and can improve naturally by simply talking with native speakers on the topics of interest.
If the answer is yes,
AJATT recommends practicing by imitating native speakers.
This is done through shadowing exercises.</p>
<p>Shadowing is a language learning technique where you listen to a native speaker
and repeat what they say, trying to match their speed, rhythm, and intonation
as closely as possible.
Here's how you can go about shadowing:</p>
<ol>
<li>Choose an audio or video recording of a native speaker speaking your target language.
It could be a <a href="immersion-with-youtube.html">YouTube</a> video or an audiobook.
Obtain the text version, the transcript of the recording as well.</li>
<li>Listen to the recording.
Start shadowing by repeating what the speaker says,
trying to match their speed, rhythm, intonation and pitch accent as closely as possible.</li>
<li>Record yourself.
Pay attention to your own pronunciation and try to correct any mistakes you notice.</li>
</ol>
<p>You can repeat what the native speaker says after they say it or simultaneously, at the same time.
There appears to be no consensus on which way is better.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/whats-the-best-way-to-make-use-of-an-italki-teacher.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/whats-the-best-way-to-make-use-of-an-italki-teacher.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 02:33:03 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How much of my immersion should I understand?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>The answer is simple: you should aim to understand 100% of your immersion.
Everything.
One hundred percent.
Every time you come across an unfamiliar word or phrase,
it is a problem, and it has to be fixed.
Don't hesitate to take action, you've got thousands of words to acquire.
The ultimate goal is to reach a point where each unknown word is so rare
that it stands out, and you just can't ignore it.</p>
<p>When starting to learn a new language,
it's normal to understand nothing at first.
The first step is to train your ears to hear the sounds of the language, which can take time.
The next step is to immerse for thousands of hours and learn lots of grammar and vocabulary,
required to reach fluency.
The more time you invest, the more your language skills will improve.</p>
<p>To tackle the initial challenge of not understanding,
it's advisable to prioritize <a href="basic-vocabulary.html">basic vocabulary</a> in the beginning.
By spending your first month or two on learning the most common words of the language
you can quickly improve your comprehension and
start to understand everyday conversations quite well.
You can then continue learning by mining example sentences from your input,
starting with slice of life shows
and eventually moving towards more sophisticated media.</p>
<p><em>Frontloading</em> the most frequently used words is perhaps one of the most significant techniques
in mastering the target language,
which I personally found very helpful in the beginning.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-much-of-my-immersion-should-i-understand.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/how-much-of-my-immersion-should-i-understand.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 18:37:32 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Japanese support for Anki</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p><a href="setting-up-anki.html">Anki</a>
can be used
to learn a variety of different subjects,
including languages.
What makes Anki such a fantastic tool for Japanese learners is the vast array of plugins or &quot;add-ons&quot;
that extend its functionality.
One of the most useful add-ons for learning Japanese is
<a href="https://ankiweb.net/shared/info/1344485230">AJT Japanese</a>.
Its main features include
adding furigana,
adding pitch accent information,
and adding pronunciation audio files to Anki cards.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/anki-japanese-support.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/anki-japanese-support.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 12:36:53 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Is music a good way to learn Japanese?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>I do my Anki reps and sometimes watch vbijin,
but I find myself listening to Japanese music more than anything.
I get that song lyrics aren't representative of real sentences,
but surely there's still things of worth in there.
I like Tatsuro Yamashita, Jody is a banger.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have touched on this topic in several places of the guide,
but I'm going to reiterate everything here
since it's easier to read one Q&amp;A than the entire guide.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-music-a-good-way-to-learn-japanese.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-music-a-good-way-to-learn-japanese.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 20:57:29 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Is it OK to sentence mine during free-flow immersion instead of intensive-immersion?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>The difference between <a href="active-immersion.html#free-flow-immersion">free-flow</a>
and <a href="active-immersion.html#intensive-immersion">intensive</a> immersion
is that free-flow is more passive and relaxed,
while intensive immersion involves actively looking things up and making cards.
During intensive immersion,
it is expected that you make flashcards
as you are already putting in the effort to look up words.</p>
<p>However, sentencing mining during free-flow immersion instead of intensive immersion is a viable option.
If that is the method that works best for you,
then go for it.
But you'll have to rearrange the process of making your flashcards.
When watching a movie, for example, you usually pause to look up an unknown word
and then make a <a href="discussing-various-card-templates.html#targeted-sentence-cards">targeted sentence card</a>
with a chosen dictionary definition.
But since free-flow immersion doesn't involve looking up words,
when you come across a new word,
you just make a card with the sentence.
In MPV with mpvacious you can press one button to make a card.
The key is not to interrupt the flow.
Then, you would dedicate a period of time to go through the new flashcards
and add dictionary definitions, mark the target words, and include other relevant information.</p>
<p>If making cards during free-flow immersion is more effective for you,
there is no reason not to do it.
I do it myself when I feel like it.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-ok-to-mine-during-free-flow-immersion.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/is-it-ok-to-mine-during-free-flow-immersion.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 23:29:45 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Are there potential downsides of using audio-only content like podcasts as the main source of free-flow immersion?</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>There's really no need to confine yourself to audio-only content,
such as podcasts,
for free-flow immersion,
as audio-visual content like movies and TV shows will be far more effective.</p>
<p>If you primarily learn through audio and visual materials,
you will develop strong listening skills.
This proficiency will be of great value in the long term.
If you acquire your target language through listening
before starting to read,
the way your brain will process the language
will be more in line with that of native speakers.
However, native speakers don't limit themselves to listening alone.
By excluding visual media you are lowering your comprehension for no reason at all.</p>
<p>Audio-visual content gives you all the benefits of audio-only content,
and your comprehension will be much higher thanks to the visual cues.
On the other hand,
podcasts can be difficult to understand,
particularly for beginner learners.
They lack transcripts,
visual context
and anything else that could help you understand what is being said.
In my experience, podcasts are virtually indistinguishable from white noise
until you reach a solid intermediate level.
So, there are huge downsides to
relying solely on audio-only content for free-flow immersion,
as it will drastically slow down vocabulary acquisition.
I would recommend audio-visual content instead.</p>
<p>I deem audio-only free-flow immersion to be comparable to passive immersion.
It is unlikely that during listening one can maintain the same
level of focus and attention as when watching.
While it is acceptable to use podcasts for passive immersion,
as long as you understand the language used,
it is advisable to choose a medium that you have previously watched actively.</p>
<p>The rate of acquisition also depends on what you do during intensive immersion.
If during intensive immersion you read novels, comic books, or watch movies and TV shows,
while looking up words and mining sentences, then you will be learning vocabulary faster,
and the downsides of using audio-only content during free-flow immersion will be less significant.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href="tag_faq.html">faq</a></p>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/audio-as-main-source-of-free-flow-immersion.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/audio-as-main-source-of-free-flow-immersion.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 03:34:41 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Setting up GoldenDict</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>GoldenDict is a libre dictionary application for GNU/Linux and other OSes.
Like <a href="setting-up-qolibri.html">Qolibri</a>, it lets you search multiple dictionaries at the same time
so for every word you look up you immediately get a number of definitions.
GoldenDict is a great tool for language learners,
and it becomes especially helpful
when one switches from bilingual dictionaries to monolingual dictionaries.
It can aid during the monolingual transition
thanks to the ability to look up many words at once in separate tabs,
simplifying recursive look-ups.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/setting-up-goldendict.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/setting-up-goldendict.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 05:30:22 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Passive immersion</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>When we talk about immersion, we usually divide it into active and passive.
<em>Active immersion</em> requires full attention to the content
and can be practiced through reading and watching content in the target language.
<em>Passive immersion</em> means listening to the language while engaging in other activities.
When listening passively you're not fully focused on the content,
instead you're doing something else
while having the speech in your target language play in the background.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/passive-immersion.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/passive-immersion.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 00:45:18 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Active immersion</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Active immersion is a crucial part of language learning
and requires full attention to the content you are consuming.
In this article,
we will look in more detail at what active immersion is and how to practice it.
We will also discuss the different types of active immersion,
and how to deal with the ambiguity that can arise when immersing.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/active-immersion.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/active-immersion.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 00:13:10 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Reading books</title>
<author>Tatsumoto</author>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Reading a book is a simple process.
You don't need much technology to read a book.
In contrast,
when watching a movie,
you need software that can create Anki cards from the subtitles.
Or,
when reading manga,
you need an OCR tool to extract text from the images.
But to read a book, all you may need is
a dictionary on hand to look up unfamiliar words.
And a program that can open and display books, of course.
If you have a paper book, you don't even need a computer.
Nevertheless, there are some tips I'd like to discuss here.</p>
<p>In this article, we'll discuss a few tips and tricks to help make
reading books in Japanese easier and more enjoyable.</p>
<hr>]]></description>
<link>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/reading-books.html</link>
<guid>https://tatsumoto-ren.github.io/blog/reading-books.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Tatsumoto</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 11:32:56 +0300</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
